第9集:深海生物
海洋，地球上最大的栖息地
The ocean.The largest habitat on Earth,
相对于我们居住的陆地，这是显得有些荒凉
and an inhospitable place for those of us who live on land.
然而10亿年来，这里曾今是这个星球上
Yet, for a billion years,this was the only place on the planet
唯一存在生命的地方
where life existed.
如今，那些早期生命形式的的后裔在这里繁衍
Today, descendants of those early life forms continue to thrive.
它们和各种鱼类分享着海洋，数量却远超鱼类
They share the sea with fish,but outnumber them by ten to one.
它们没有骨骼
They have no backbones,
进化成无数不同的形式
and have evolved into countless different forms.
有些体型巨大，有较大的脑容量和初级智能
Some are huge, large-brained and intelligent.
有些则显得十分微小
Others are minuscule,
但正是它们一同建立了地球上最大的生物体系
yet build the largest natural structures on the planet.
它们是海洋无脊椎动物，深海中的生物
They are marine invertebrates,the creatures of the deep.
他们在海洋的各个角落殖民
They have colonised every corner of the ocean,
以许多令人难以置信的
and have a mind-boggling range of solutions
方案来解决生存难题
to the problem of staying alive.
海洋各处不是均一的
The ocean is by no means uniform.
深度的差异，温度，阳光和洋流的差异
Differences in depth, temperature,sunlight and currents
构成了特殊的挑战
pose particular challenges.
水下一英里半处，海底热泉正在喷发
One and a half miles down,these hydrothermal vents
这些从地壳裂缝喷涌出的热水
spew out super-heated water at 450 degrees Centigrade
温度高达摄氏450度
from cracks in the Earth's crust.
巨大的压力，黑暗的环境
Despite the enormous pressure,the total darkness,
严酷的高温环境
and the scaldingly-high temperatures,
生命可能就是起源于类似这样的地方
the ancestors of all life may have evolved in a place just like this.
庞贝蠕虫
Pompeii worms.
其名源于他们能在这样的火山热下生存的能力
So named for their ability to survive volcanic heat.
和周围的蟹以及长达两米的管状蠕虫的分享这些水下火山通气口
They share the vents with crabs and two-metre-long tube worms.
他们只能生存在这里，因为他们需要以
They can only survive here because they are able to feed on bacteria
那些在通气口周围异常丰富的菌类作为食物
that thrive around the vents.
这种栖息地极为罕见
These colonies are extremely rare.
难怪多数生物都聚集在靠近海面之处
Not surprisingly, most life thrives
这里的食物十分丰富
nearer the surface,where feeding is considerably easier.
这些是磷虾，微小的虾状甲壳类动物
These are krill,tiny shrimp-like crustaceans.
虾群可以达到惊人的数量 - 6万立方米
Swarms can reach astounding numbers -60,000 per cubic metre.
在晚上，他们浮上海面以浮游生物为食
During the night they rise towards the surface to feed on plankton.
科尔特斯海，墨西哥
Here, in the Sea of Cortez,off Mexico,
虾群引来了各种捕食者
the swarms attract hunters of all kinds,
从座头鲸到各种肉食性的鱼类
from humpback whales to shoals of predatory fish.
还有一个猎手
Yet another hunter arrives.
从深海远道而来
It's one from the deep.
美洲大赤鱿
A Humboldt squid.
身长两米，在当地被视为食人怪兽
Two metres long, they have a local reputation as man-eaters.
一只美洲大赤鱿就够猎物们担忧了
Alone, they are formidable enough...
但来的是一群...
but this is a pack...
..数十成百，蜂拥而来
..of hundreds.
它们是很聪明的猎手,视觉系统十分特殊
They are highly intelligent hunters.Their eyesight is exceptional.
它们拥有强大的触角，吸盘周围有多达七万个环状钩
They have powerful tentacles,suckers ringed with 70,000 hooks
还有能撕裂肌肉的尖锐喙嘴
and a razor-sharp beak for tearing through flesh.
现在这些鱼发现到情况不妙
Now the fish find that they are under attack
聚集起来抵御外敌
and so group together for safety.
但这些乌贼也是以群体行动
But the Humboldt squid work as a team,
将鱼群驱赶到岩石附近
herding the fish against the rocks.
这些乌贼发出的红色和白色的闪光，
被认为不仅仅用于惊扰它们的猎物
It's thought that the squidflash red and
white not only to confuse their prey,
也是他们正用来协调攻击猎物的信号
but also to signal to each other when they are about to attack.
这些乌贼的数量增长的很快
Humboldt squid numbers are growing rapidly.
但它们仍然保持神秘
But they remain mysterious.
如同出现时一样迅速，它们又消失在深海之中
As fast as they arrived, they disappear back into the deep.
距离南极800英里，在活火山埃里伯斯的巨大阴影中
800 miles from the South Pole, in the
shadow of a smouldering Mount Erebus.
冬季的气温下降到可怕的零下40度
Winter temperatures are a punishing minus 40.
这里也许是最没可能发现海洋生物的地方
This, perhaps, is the last place you might expect to find marine life.
现在是极地的早春
Now it's the beginning of the polar spring,
也是这个月的月首
and for the first time in months,
阳光透过冰层，轻撩入海
light reaches the sea beneath the ice.
一年中酷寒和黑暗的时节
It's extremely cold and completely dark for much of the year,
但在冰下的海洋深处，环境大相径庭
so conditions are not unlike those of the deep ocean.
在麦克默多海峡，生机盎然
Yet, in McMurdo Sound,life flourishes.
这里的生物生长极为缓慢
The creatures here grow extremely slowly.
但这并不意味着他们可以活到多老或长到多大
But that does mean they can reach a great age and great size,
而是体现于它们令人惊讶的数量
and they occur in surprisingly large numbers.
身长三米的食肉蠕虫
Three-metre-long, carnivorous nemertean worms.
红海星
Red sea stars
海胆铺成了海底地毯
and urchins carpet the sea floor.
这个怪物一般的蠕虫几乎无所不食
This monster-worm will eat almost anything
不断地搜索海底寻找食物
and is constantly scanning the sea floor for food.
如此众多的生物云集于此是因为...
Animals are swarming here in such numbers because of this...
一只死掉的海豹
..a dead seal pup.
对它们来说，分量如此丰盛的大餐
Such a great quantity of food
也许十年才会出现一次
may only arrive once in ten years.
但是海豹的尸体对它们来说并不容易被消灭
But a seal's body won't be easy to eat.
纽虫有一个叉形的鼻状物
Nemerteans have a snout like a harpoon,
使它们能够穿刺尸体的皮肤
that enables them to puncture the skin of the corpse.
更艰苦的工作由海星来完成
It's harder work for the sea stars.
它们进食时要从嘴巴吐出胃
They feed by pushing out their stomachs through their mouths.
通过海星的胃对海豹皮肤的咀食
As this sea star presses its stomach against the seal's skin,
它分泌的消化液分解着海豹的表皮组织
it secretes digestive juices that dissolve the seal's tissue.
但这需要一些时间
But that takes time.
整个夏天，这些拾荒者都会在这里进食
These scavengers will feed here throughout the summer,
直到海豹只剩下一个骨架
until all that remains of the seal
will be a skeleton, stripped bare.
浅水只是海洋世界的一小部分
The shallows are only a tiny part of the marine world.
其中九成是开放的水域
90% of it is open water.
洋流携带的生命绵延数千英里
Its currents carry life for thousands of miles.
水母是这片水下游牧场的主人
The masters of this nomadic existence are jellyfish.
一个在广阔海洋中漂流的生命也许是孤独的
A life spent drifting in the empty ocean could be a lonely one...
但这只水母并不孤单
but not for this jellyfish.
奥里利亚
Aurelia.
出现这庞大的水母群并非偶然
Swarms like this are not accidental.
这些水母是一起孵化的
These individuals all hatched together
在一个温度和海流都恰到好处的时候
when the temperature and currents were just right.
这个时机使得它们能正好赶上夏末
Their timing has ensured that they can make the most
浮游生物生长的旺盛期，有尽可能多的食物
of feeding on a late-summer plankton bloom.
水母没有大脑和血液
Jellyfish have no brain and no blood.
但它们有眼点，可以分辨明暗
But they do have eyespots that enable them to
tell the difference between light and dark.
它们通过眼前这种
And they can move independently of the current
喷水推进的简单形式移动
by a simple form of jet propulsion.
所有的水母都会用它们带刺的触角来捕捉食物。
All jellyfish have stinging tentacles with which to catch their food.
它们脉动自己的身体，用触角困住浮游生物
As they pulse their bodies,the tentacles trap plankton,
然后通过它们的嘴吞下食物
which is then passed towards their mouth in the centre.
一个数量达到十万的水母群
A swarm of 100,000 stinging jellyfish
或许能吓跑来掠食的动物
might seem a daunting prospect for a predator...
但这个家伙不同
..but not for this one.
一只巨大的炒蛋水母
A huge fried egg jellyfish.
它是冷血杀手
It is a killer.
它的武器是涵盖在触手表面的鱼叉状的细胞
Its weapons are harpoon-like cells that cover its tentacles.
当它们碰触到一个受害者，就会发动攻击
When they come into contact with a victim, they spear it.
然后享受它们的猎物
The fried egg then hauls in its prey.
很少有水母能幸运的挣扎逃脱
A few lucky Aurelia do manage to pull themselves free.
大多数受害者都...
But for the majority,there is only one outcome...
难逃一死
Death.
和很多海洋无脊椎动物一样，海蜇
Jellyfish, like a great many marine invertebrates,
具有柔软，脆弱的身体
have soft, vulnerable bodies.
靠带刺的细胞保护自己
They are protected by stinging cells.
也有一些其他类型的防御方法
But there are other kinds of defence.
例如用甲壳
Armour plating.
这些是蜘蛛蟹
These are spider crabs.
它们生命的大部分时间在深水中度过
They spend most of their lives in deep water.
但一年一次，在南澳大利亚海岸
But once a year,off the coast of Southern Australia,
有25万的蟹会有一次远征浅滩的旅程
a quarter of a million crabs set off on a long journey to the shallows.
因为它们都有一个同样的问题有待解决
They are here because they all share a problem.
每只蟹都在过去的一年时间里穿着同一件马甲
Each crab has been wearing the same suit of armour for a year now.
越来越紧，很不舒服
And it's getting uncomfortably tight.
所以每个蟹终于要摆脱它的外壳，制造一个更大的
So each crab eventually has to shed its shell and produce a bigger one.
替换旧壳，显然是个麻烦的过程
Replacing an old shell is understandably a tricky process.
首先，这些蟹在旧壳生长出完全新的皮肤
First the crab grows an entirely new skin within the old shell.
然后，弯曲自己的身体，迫使其旧壳从背面裂开
It then flexes its body to force its
shell to split along the back...
再小心翼翼的从裂口爬出来
..before gingerly backing itself out.
蜘蛛蟹聚集于此不仅为了换壳，也是为了交配
The spider crabs are not only here to moult, but to mate.
他们热情洋溢，抓住时机繁衍后代
And they grab the opportunity with considerable enthusiasm.
但这样大场面的集会也不免有个害处
Coming together in such numbers does however have a drawback.
容易吸引天敌
It attracts predators.
这是刺
A stingray.
尽管有这么多潜在的猎物
Despite there being so many potential prey,
刺似乎视而不见
the stingray seems to ignore them.
也许是因为蟹聚集在一起，它不好下手
Perhaps there's safety in numbers...
尽管并非所有的蜘蛛蟹
..although not all the crabs
都准备以此保护自己
are prepared to rely on it.
蟹群开始警觉起来
Alarm spreads amongst the crabs.
事实上，它们中的大多数都是安全的。这条鳐鱼刺挑剔
But in fact, most of them are safe.This ray is being very choosy.
这只对那些壳最软的蟹感兴趣
It's only interested in the softest shelled,
大多数是那些刚刚换壳的
most recently moulted crabs.
一旦被它选为目标，绝无生还的机会
Once a target is singled out,there is no escape.
当它们的新的装甲硬化以后
When their new armour has hardened,
这些蟹就可以留下那些老旧的空壳
the crabs return to the comparative safety of the deep,
安全的返回海水深处
leaving behind only their old, empty shells.
和蜘蛛蟹一样，多数海洋生物的行为只是通过简单的神经系统来控制
Like spider crabs, the behaviour of most marine
creatures is controlled by a very simple nervous system.
但也有例外
But there are exceptions.
这种乌贼就是海洋中最聪明的动物之一。
This cuttlefish is one of the cleverest animals in the ocean.
这只母乌贼有一个非常大的大脑
She has a very large brain.
事实上它大脑与身体的比例超过了大多数鱼类和爬行动物
In fact, it's larger for her size than that of most fish or reptiles.
它的生存经历往往复杂且充满了各种阴谋
Her life is both complex and full of intrigue.
澳洲巨乌贼通常独居
Giant Australian cuttlefish usually live alone,
但它们短暂的一生中必须聚集起来交配一次
but once in their short lives they must come together to mate.
随着它逐渐展现传统的交配意愿
As she approaches the traditional mating grounds,
一只体型较大的雄乌贼开始表现出对她的兴趣
one of the largest males starts to show interest in her.
她将他带到一个远离他的竞争对手的，更为安静的地点
She moves him away from his rivals to a quieter spot -
在这里，她将可以安全的产卵
a place where she will be able to lay her eggs in safety.
在用一只触手在她的嘴附近将
The male takes the female in his arms and turns her to face him,
精子袋弄开一个口以后，雄性乌贼
before using one of his arms to pass sacks of sperm
将她揽入怀中，面向自己
to an opening near her mouth.
交配以后，他徘徊在她周围
Once mated, he hovers over her,
站岗警戒到她产下卵为止
standing guard until she's laid her eggs.
但他还有一个问题
But he's got a problem.
雄性乌贼的数量4倍于雌性
Males outnumber females four to one.
因此，保有配偶是一场持久的斗争
So keeping her to himself is a constant battle.
这位体型更大的竞争对手很难被吓走
This larger rival is more difficult to intimidate.
墨鱼可以使它们的皮肤图案产生剧烈的变化
Cuttlefish can make very dramatic changes to their skin pattern
借以表明他们的情绪
in order to signal their moods.
在身侧显现的鲜艳色彩和条纹
Flushes of bright colour and stripes that pulse along his side,
都在警告它的对手离开这里
tell the rival to keep off.
大多数竞争对手都会怯步于这个阶段
Most rivals back down at this stage,but not this one.
但这只始终不为所动，尽管警告的信号变得越来越强
Although the male's flashing signals get more and more emphatic,
最后它别无选择选择，只能打斗
in the end,he has no choice but to fight.
赢了!它又可以回来继续守卫它的爱妻了
Victory! And the male can return to guard his female.
墨鱼之间可以进行不起的沟通，但也有黑暗的一面
Cuttlefish are great communicators,but there is a flip side -
它们也能成为欺诈高手
they can also be masters of deception.
这只身形短小的雄乌贼不足以赢得交配的机会，但它有另外一个计划...
This male is too small to fight for a mate, but he has another plan -
它显得鬼鬼祟祟
and it's sneaky.
谨慎的接近这对乌贼
He approaches the couple cautiously,
在身体前方卷曲触角
holding his tentacles tucked up at the front,
伪装成一只想要交配的母乌贼
mimicking a female that wants to mate.
为了伪装的更完美
To complete his disguise,
它将身体的颜色也变的和雌性一样
he changes colour to appear even more like a female.
站岗的雄乌贼似乎信以为真了，也许他认为他的鸿运当头
The guarding male seems convinced,maybe he thinks his luck is in -
又一只母乌贼被自己征服了
another female to add to his conquests.
而这个男扮女装狡诈的家伙
The sly, cross-dressing male
小心翼翼的慢慢接近雌性乌贼
edges closer and closer to the female, holding his nerve.
只要避免了在拥抱雌性交配时被原配赶走，他就安全了
As long as he avoids being grabbed in
a mating embrace, the sneak is safe.
也许雌性乌贼猜到了这家伙的身份可疑
At what point the female guesses his true identity is unclear,
但她并不挑剔，在男友粗壮的触角下
but she isn't choosy,and surreptitiously mates with him
在其毫不知觉的情况下与外来者交配
right under the larger male's tentacles.
现在是她产卵的时间了
It's time for the female to lay her eggs.
她用来自两个雄性的精子，使自己的卵一一受精
Using the sperm from both males,she fertilises her eggs one by one
将它们粘在一个隐蔽的岩石缝隙中
and glues them to a rock in a hidden crevice.
也算一种运气，她现在有一批混合的后代
With luck,she will now have a mix of offspring.
有些会长成的壮硕的雄性乌贼，另一些则像她的另一个丈夫
Some may become masterful males,and others, little sneaks.
她选择随遇而安
She'll have all the bases covered.
不列颠哥伦比亚沿海水域
The coastal waters of British Columbia.
这里生活着身长可达4米的太平洋巨型章鱼
Home to this four-metre-long Pacific Giant Octopus.
她是强大的肉食生物，但此刻她并无心狩猎
She is a formidable predator,but at the moment hunting isn't on her mind.
她刚刚完成了第一次交配
She has just mated for the first time.
现在她正在寻找一个安全的庇护所
And now she's searching for a safe refuge.
她显得十分慎重
She makes her choice carefully.
在未来的几个月里，这里将是她的家
This is going to be her home for many months to come.
也是她的育儿所
It's her nursery den.
洞顶上挂着她产下的100000枚卵
100,000 eggs hang from its ceiling,
她将用生命来守护它们
and she's guarding them with her life.
失去她的呵护，它们可能会被天敌吃掉
Without her to protect them,they would be eaten by predators,
或者因为环境而死掉
or become diseased.
她用触角爱抚着它们
She caresses them with her tentacles,
确保表面不会有藻类生长，赶开想来偷食的鱼类
ensuring that algae don't grow on them, and that fish don't eat them.
她一直保持卵周围的水流处于流动状态
She constantly keeps the water moving around them,
以便它们有充足的氧气供应
so they're well-supplied with oxygen.
长达半年的时间里，她会一直照看它们
She cares for them for six months,
在此期间，她会停止觅食
and during all this time,she doesn't eat a thing.
现在，它们即将孵化了
And now, as they are hatching,
而她，正在迈向死亡
she is dying.
一天晚上，章鱼宝宝们终于出世了
One night,as the baby octopus emerge,
她用最后的力气对它们鼓动水流，将它们送入大海的怀抱
she jets water over them for the last time, helping them on their way.
她的生命也就此落幕
This will be her final act.
这是她生命中唯一一次生育
This is the only time she will reproduce,
她牺牲自己的生命给后代一个良好的生存机会
and to give her young their best chance, she sacrifices her life.
海洋中最大也是最凶恶的海星从深海中出现
Out of the depths comes one of the largest and most aggressive starfish in the ocean.
向日葵海星
足有垃圾桶盖那么大
a giant sunstar the size of a dustbin lid.
每支触臂上都覆盖着许多感觉敏锐的管状吸盘，这是一个厉害角色
It's a hunter. Each arm is covered by super-sensitive tube feet,
利用管状足，它能通过触摸和嗅觉探测到猎物
that can detect prey by touch and smell.
但它似乎比较偏爱腐肉
But the sunstar is also partial to carrion,
它发现了巨型章鱼的母亲的尸体
and it detects the carcass of the giant octopus mother.
用触角上的小型吸盘敲打着尸体
The miniature suckers on its feet clamp on to the corpse,
然后把它拖出洞穴
and drag it out of the cave.
其它的食腐生物也赶来参加盛宴
Other scavengers rush to join the feast.
尽管身为一个可怕的食肉动物
Although it's a fearsome predator,
向日葵海星也并非一路上横行无忌
Pycnopodia doesn't have it all its own way.
这些海胆不足以用速度来逃跑
These sea urchins aren't speedy enough to escape,
但它们也有厉害的防御招术
but they do have a formidable defence.
面对这些锐利的刺，想要通过是件困难的事情
The sharp spines are hard to get past,
更何况海胆可以独立的运动它的棘刺
and, what's more, the urchins can move each spine independently,
夹住海星的触手
pinching the starfish's probing arms.
如同被一群顽童组成的部队困住
Trapped by an army of urchins,
向日葵海星被一只巨大的帝王蟹发现了
Pycnopodia is spotted by an enormous king crab.
向日葵海星碰到了真正的对手
Pycnopodia has more than met its match,
几秒钟内帝王蟹就卸下了它的一只手臂
and within seconds,the crab rips off one of its arms.
但这对海星来说只是暂时的不便
But that is just a temporary inconvenience.
它能够迅速再生出失去的肢体
Starfish are able to quickly regrow a lost limb.
无脊椎动物想要令人印象深刻似乎需要有巨大的体型
The most impressive invertebrates may seem to be the giants,
但事实上一些最微小的生物也具有重大的影响力
but in fact it's some of the smallest that can make the biggest impact.
这个岛的每平方英寸都是被建造出来的
Every square inch of this island has been created
一个活的，不断增长的上层建筑
by an ever-growing, living superstructure,
珊瑚礁
a coral reef.
几千年的积累达到了这样大的规模
It's taken thousands of years to reach this size,
而这一切开始于只有针尖般大小的生物
and it all began with creatures smaller than a pinhead.
珊瑚礁并非在哪儿都能生长
A reef can't be built just anywhere,
首先它需要有一个坚实的基础
it needs something to give it a firm footing.
这样的沉船残骸，就是一个良好的基础
A wreck like this provides an excellent foundation.
一旦它沉淀在海床上
As soon as it settles on the sea bed,
残骸就开始受到入侵者的攻击
the wreck comes under attack from invaders -
浮游生物，通过洋流来到这里
plankton, carried here by ocean currents.
这些是微观下的藤壶和海棉幼虫
These are the microscopic larvae of barnacles, sponges,
而最重要的是，珊瑚虫
and, most importantly, corals.
幼虫必须依附到残骸上
The larvae must attach themselves to the wreck.
一旦成功，他们就开始生长成名为珊瑚水螅体的年轻珊瑚
Once there, they can develop into young corals called polyps.
但他们生长起来十分缓慢
But the polyps are very slow-growing,
而且存在着大量与入侵者之间的竞争
and there is lots of competition from other invaders.
藻类迅速覆盖沉船
Algae quickly cover the wreck,
对年轻的珊瑚来说这是个严重的问题
and that's a problem for the young coral.
藻类会吸引食草动物
Algae attract grazers.
这些珊瑚水栖体面临着在站稳脚跟之前就被吃掉的危险
The polyps are in danger of being eaten
beforethey've even got a proper foothold.
如果条件合适
If conditions are right,
幸存者可以继续建立一个礁
the survivors can go on to build a reef.
位置的选择至关重要
Position is critical.
如果太深，就没有足够的阳光供给珊瑚生长
Too deep, and not enough light will reach the corals for them to grow.
而太浅则有在退潮时被暴露在空气中的危险
Too shallow, and they risk being exposed to the air at low tide.
对于珊瑚礁能真正蓬勃生长而言
For the reef to really flourish,
也需要处在洋流的路径上以便有充足的食物
it also needs to be in the path of currents carrying food.
大约五六年的时间以后
Fast-forward half a dozen years or so,
沉船将开始显现出肉眼可见的
and the wreck will begin to show the first signs
珊瑚礁的最初迹象
of corals visible to the naked eye.
十年以后，景象完全发生改变
A decade later,and the wreck will be transformed.
成千上万的珊瑚水栖体形成珊瑚礁的硬壳表面
Thousands of polyps will form coral heads that encrust its surface.
这艘船在第二次世界大战时被击沉
This ship was sunk during the Second World War,
时间已足够让珊瑚礁完成其生长历程中的重要过程
and there has been enough time for a substantial reef to develop.
经过几十年的发展
After decades of growth,
不同品种的珊瑚主导着沉船周围的具体领域
different species of corals dominate particular areas of the wreck.
增长最快的类型适宜生长在边缘和四周
The fastest-growing types grow best on the edges and overhangs,
逐渐接近甚至冒出水面
reaching far out into the water,and up to the light.
它们只需要一小块地方立足
They need only a small area to establish themselves,
但他们能迅速成长扩张到其他区域
yet they can rapidly grow dozens of plates, or branches,
长满了珊瑚体，吸收尽可能多的光线
crammed with polyps, to gather as much light as possible.
生长较慢，更结实和坚固的珊瑚，如这些脑珊瑚
Slower-growing, much more robust corals like these brain corals,
对于崛起中的珊瑚礁来说更适合在中心位置生长
are better suited to the heart of the developing reef.
可以使得珊瑚礁更加稳固
It's these that give the reef their structure and permanence.
这里有着近500个品种的珊瑚
There could be nearly 500 different species here,
都很努力的在这锈迹斑斑的废铁上赢取立足之地
each striving to win a foothold on the rusting hulk.
珊瑚的生活节奏似乎非常缓慢
The pace of life for corals may seem to be so slow,
这很难想象会有任何冲突
that it's hard to imagine that there is any conflict here.
但每当夜幕低垂，珊瑚礁上的气氛开始变化
But, as night falls,the mood on the reef changes.
珊瑚，事实上是非常凶悍的
Corals are, in fact,extremely aggressive,
会不惜战斗至死以扩大其领土
and will fight to the death to expand their territory.
没有光荣的撤退
There can be no honourable retreat,
从表面来看，赢的一方会吃掉活着的敌人
a winner will, literally,eat its enemy alive.
沿着战线，它们的战斗人员涌出珊瑚水栖体
Along the battle front, the polyps of both combatants extrude their guts,
用长线状纤维覆盖它们的对手
long thread-like filaments,over their opponents.
战场边缘，那些留下的被摧毁的珊瑚体
At the fringe, all that remains of the destroyed polyps
就是它们的亡骸
are their skeletons.
消化速度更快的一方取得胜利
The coral that can digest fastest,wins.
珊瑚在他们的同伴的尸体的骨骼上不断增长
Corals constantly grow over the skeletons of their dead comrades,
建立起一个越来越大的礁石
building a bigger and bigger reef.
每年一次
Then, just once a year,
11月满月后的几天
a few days after the November full moon, the corals take part
珊瑚会有一次大规模的产卵活动
in a mass spawning event.
数百万的卵子和精子被释放到水中
Millions of eggs and sperm are released into the water,
结合，发展成幼虫漂移，再去搜索在一个地方定居
and join, to develop into larvae that drift in search of a place to settle.
最后，残骸的每一寸表面都将成为珊瑚的殖民地
Eventually, every inch of the wreck's surface will be colonised.
生锈的钢铁隐没消失，只剩下珊瑚礁蓬勃生长
The steel will rust away,and the reef will be on its own.
大部分珊瑚礁的成长历程中并没有这样的残骸提供帮助
Most reefs grow without the help of a wreck to start them off.
但只要时间足够，它们也可以创造出庞大至大堡礁这样的
But, given time, they can create something as huge as this,
地球上最大的生命体聚集的的结构
the Great Barrier Reef, the largest living structure on Earth.
其中生命的多样性堪比热带雨林
A coral reef rivals even a rainforest for its diversity of life.
珊瑚也被发现于食物非常稀少在水域中
Yet corals like this are found in waters where food is very scarce.
在这里所有的生物都采取特有的
All the creatures here have had to adopt a different
和高度专业化的方式收集每一份营养残料
and highly specialised way to gather every nourishing scrap.
圣诞树蠕虫钻进珊瑚中以作为保护自己
Christmas tree worms bore into the coral's skeleton for protection,
用羽状的鳃来扇取食物碎屑
swirling out and grabbing food particles with their feathery gills.
这些珊瑚藤壶虫其实和龙虾是亲戚
Coral barnacles are, in fact,related to lobsters.
它们身体躺着
They lie on their backs,
挥动着他们的脚去收集任何飘过的食物
waving their feet to gather any food floating past.
螃蟹演变出许多不同的方法去收集食物
Crabs have evolved many different ways of gathering food.
这只瓷蟹的前腿上有许多细丝
This porcelain crab has a fan of filaments on his front legs.
拳击蟹在每个小拳头上附上一个很小的海莲花
A boxer crab attaches a tiny sea anemone to each fist.
它用它们那粘性的花须来防御敌人
As well as for defence, he uses their sticky tentacles
以及收集附近零散的食物
to gather passing plankton.
猩猩蟹的全身都有黏性细毛
This orangutan crab's whole body is coated with sticky hairs,
现在看来，可能有点黏过头了
in this case,perhaps just a bit too sticky!
这个奇怪的生物是一个海参
This strange creature is a sea cucumber.
它利用其触角从沉积物中攫取食物
It uses its tentacles to grab food from the sediment.
这里也有的猎食者光顾
There are hunters here too,
比如这些海蛞蝓
like these nudibranchs, or sea slugs.
鲜艳的的颜色警示着它们是有毒的生物
Their vibrant colours are a warning that they're toxic.
有超过3000种生物，只会狩猎特定的猎物
There are over 3,000 species,many hunt just one specific prey.
有些则互相捕食
Some hunt each other.
帝王虾尽可能多为它的寄主制造毒素
This emperor shrimp makes the most of the poisonous nature of its host.
而作为回报
But, it's a rather one-sided affair.
它得到了食物，保护以及免费的乘骑
As it feeds, the shrimp gets protection and a free ride.
有些虾尝试发展一种更加平衡的关系
Other shrimps have developed a more balanced relationship.
有些甚至征求合作伙伴
Some even solicit for partners.
这些为了得到食物而翩翩起舞
These dance for their dinner.
这些正在向四周的过客们告知
And these advertise to passers-by
它们正在营业
that they are open for business.
他们是寄生虫处理小组
They are a parasite removal team,
为生活在珊瑚礁群中的各种鱼类提供服务
providing a service for countless fish on the reef,
包括这些可能很乐意吃掉它们的客人
including those that could happily eat them.
它们英勇服务的回报，是一顿大餐
In return for their bravery,they get a meal that comes to them.
最这些微小的生物建立起来的珊瑚礁
Coral reefs,built by the tiniest of creatures,
仅占用了不到两百分之一的海床面积
occupy less than half of one per cent of the ocean's floor.
却为1/4的海洋物种的生存提供了条件
Yet they support a quarter of all marine species.
海洋无脊椎动物
Marine creatures,all without backbones,
珊瑚，墨鱼，螃蟹等等
from corals, to cuttlefish, to crabs,
构成了海洋生命的大部分
make up the majority of life in the oceans.
它们对海洋以外的世界
But they have also had a surprisingly important impact
也产生了重要的影响
beyond the marine world.
正是这些动物的尸体和骨骸
Their fossilised bodies, shells and skeletons
形成了如今覆盖亚洲，欧洲及美洲
form the limestone and chalk that now covers huge tracts
大片区域的石灰层
of Asia, Europe, and the Americas.
它们虽小，但随着其20.0亿年的历史
They may be small, but over their two billion-year history,
它们改变了整个世界
they have, literally,changed the world.
为了展现这种改变的经过
To capture some of the sequences in this episode,
摄制组不得不深入未知的水下领域
the Life team had to take underwater
filming into uncharted territory.
一次摄影意味着要在冰层下两米的地方待上数个星期
One shoot meant spending weeks diving under two metres of ice,
在水温较高的地方铺设一个
another involved laying the foundation for a new coral reef
珊瑚礁的基础
in the tropics.
一艘沉船是珊瑚生长的理想地点
A sunken ship can make an ideal location for corals to grow.
出于这样的考虑
So, with this in mind,
摄制组决定迎接一个挑战...
the Life team set themselves a challenge...
人为制造一艘沉船
to make their very own shipwreck.
经过几个月的搜寻
After months of searching,
它们在巴哈马找到一艘合适的船
they find a boat in the Bahamas that might be suitable.
但在将它沉入海底之前还有很多工作要做
But there's a lot to do
before it can be sunk to the sea bed.
这艘旧船已经在码头搁置了8年
Apparently it's been here for eight years on the jetty.
所有的隔热玻璃都已脱落
All this fibreglass insulation has all got to be removed
全是手动的泵，伊恩
and it's all hands to the pump, Ian.
我们得去换套工作服
We've got to get a pair of overalls.
大家不得不收起相机，亲自清理
The team have to put away their
cameras and get their hands dirty.
这可是艘50吨的船
I've got a 50-tonne boat,
我却只能用刮漆刀来把它清理干净!
and I'm trying to clean it with a paint scraper!
将船彻底清理干净
Thoroughly cleaning the boat
是为了增加珊瑚能在上面生存下来的机会
increases the chance that coral will grow on it,
也是为了确保它不会污染到环境
and ensures it won't pollute the sea.
这就像更衣室，是不是？
It's like Changing Rooms, isn't it?
在码头生锈了8年
After eight years rusting on the jetty,
谁也不能保证它还能浮在水上
there's no guarantee that she'll even float.
厄...我们确实找到不少洞
Well, we actually...we do have some holes.
拉上去!
All up!
让及时让这艘船就绪对检查人员来说是很困难的
To get this ship ready in time for
the inspectors is a massive task,
他们在进行着光荣的任务
and they've been doing a brilliant job.
我们正在切割甲板以便她在沉没时
We're cutting panels through
to let the water rush through
水能够流进来
when she starts sinking.
最后一点了，行了伙计们。瓦莫斯!
That's the last bit, OK, guys.Vamos!
一切都准备就绪了
Shipshape at last.
现在这艘船已经被仔细清理和认真检查过了，已经准备好沉没
Well, she's clean,she's been inspected,and she's ready to be sunk.
还有什么可能出错的地方？
What can go wrong now?
电视：'这里有最新的迪安...'
TELEVISION: 'Here's the very latest with Dean...'
随着飓风迪安的末端登陆
As the tail end of Hurricane Dean sweeps through,
摄制组不得不暂时搁浅计划
the team are forced to put their plans on hold.
电视：'风速达150英里每小时的飓风...'
TELEVISION: '..winds of 150 miles an hour...'
好运似乎还是没有站在他们一边
Luck doesn't seem to be on their side.
但是，两天后天气终于转好
But, two days later,good weather returns.
吊车终于能开来了!
Here comes a crane, finally!
整个起吊过程十分顺利
Fingers crossed, arms crossed,
legs crossed, everything's crossed!
此刻他们急切的盼望船能早点下水
They urgently need to get the boat into the water,
否则在日落前就不能到达选好的沉船地点了
or they won't reach the chosen wreck site before nightfall.
她安全地在水中行驶，到目前为止一切顺利
She's safely in the water,so far, so good.
没下去了，不错!
It floats!
这是她最后的一段航程...
Her final voyage...
摄像机被安装在甲板左右
Cameras are mounted around the deck,
以拍摄她下沉的过程
to film her sinking below the surface.
我们花了一个星期准备，今天下午终于要实施了
We've spent a week preparing for this,
and finally the afternoon's arrived.
天色不早了，我们要抓紧
But the light's going,so we have to move.
最后几个洞也在船体上切割了出来，是时候注水了
A last few holes are cut.It's time to pump in water,
然后弃船
and to abandon ship.
船员们跳入水中
The crew dive in,
支援船离开到安全距离以后，准备录制她下沉的过程
ready to film her descent,while the
support boat moves away to a safe distance.
除了等待，已经没有什么更多的事情可做了
There's nothing more to do, but wait.
开工了，看看这个!
Here we go, look at this!
如他们所希望的一样，船按照预定的轨迹缓缓下沉
She gently comes to rest, and the
right way up, just as they'd hoped.
现在，只剩下让大自然完成它的使命了
Now, it's time to let nature take its course.
船员们会在两年后回来，看看生命如何扎根其上
The crew will be back over the next
two years to see how life takes hold.
在这里，沉船有着很好的
At this site, the wreck has a very good chance
成为珊瑚的栖息地的机会
that it'll be colonised by coral.
有了运气和时间，它最终会生长成一个全面的珊瑚礁
With luck and time, it'll eventually become a full-scale reef.
与此同时，在地球的另一端
Meanwhile, at the other end of the world,
摄制组面临着截然不同的挑战
the Life team's challenge is very different.
南极洲，仅是想要到达冰面以下就不是件简单的事情
Here in Antarctica, just getting underwater will be tough.
为了能在这样一个艰难的地方工作
In order to work in such a demanding location,
摄制组需要求助于国家科学基金会
the team needed the help of the National Science Foundation,
在麦克默多极地研究站
at the McMurdo polar research station.
这里的每个人都需要能应付冰天雪地的环境
Everyone here has to be able to cope out on the ice
以防有任何紧急情况发生
if there's an emergency.
因此，摄制团队与驻扎的科学家一起进行生存训练
So the Life team joins research scientists for survival training,
以防发生任何情况
to prepare them for any situation.
甚至是这样
Even one like this.
如果有同事在雪盲中迷失是非常危险的
A colleague lost in a whiteout is very serious.
这种训练也许决定着是否能开展救援活动
This training might mean the difference between rescue, or not.
这便是应对雪盲的演习
This is supposed to simulate a whiteout,
我们正在找失踪的人
we've been looking for someone who's been lost, and you wear
因为带了头罩什么也看不见.这确实很有帮助
the bucket so you cannot see at all,and it does actually work.
在那种情况下，就是像这样眼不能视物
It's just...You can't see anything in this.
完成了必要的训练，现在是时候去潜水的地方了
With the training over, it's time to travel over the ice to the dive site,
计划是在罗斯海冰面
ready to go beneath the frozen surface of the Ross Sea.
但为了能穿过这样足以让飞机着陆的冰层
But to get through this ice,thick enough to land a jet on,
需要麦克默多钻井队专家的帮助
needs the help of McMurdo's specialist drilling team.
洞被钻开以后
Once the hole is drilled,
再将一间经过特别设计的小屋推在洞口位置
a specially designed hut is slid into position.
这将是未来一个月时间里摄制组的潜水基地
This will be the team's base for the next four weeks of diving.
好了，万事皆备。我们要去的地方就在这里...
Look, this is all we need,all we need to go in here...
一扇通往另一个世界的门
the door to another world.
所有摄制需要的设备
All the equipment the team need for the shots
都需要从这个洞搬进搬出
must come in and out of this hole.
这是在这片地球极南之地最有可能进行潜水的地方了
This is as far south as it's possible to dive.
这些冰，有8英尺厚，可能一年中有11个月都在这里
The ice, eight feet thick, it's here for 11? months of the year,
我们正在准备下去看看
and we're goin go down underneath and have a look,
究竟是一番怎么样的景象
to see just what it's like underneath there.
道格和团队其他人一起潜下
Doug and the team venture below the ice.
冰面下的景观令人惊讶，壮观无比
The under-ice landscape is both surprising and spectacular,
但他们来是为了拍摄动物
but it's the animals they've come to film.
因此，专业延时相机被移动到合适的位置
So, specialist time-lapse cameras are moved into position.
在如此的低温下，动物们的移动非常缓慢
The animals move very slowly at these freezing temperatures.
但是，通过摄像机加速500倍以后
But by using time-lapse to speed up the action 500 times,
摄制组希望能首次揭示一些这些动物的行为
the team hopes to reveal the behaviour of these creatures for the first time.
随着空气和温度的流失
With air and warmth running out for this dive,
道格选择返回水下安全线标
Doug makes his way back to the lifeline,
回到冰面
and the surface.
噢！太棒了。下里的景象非常非常漂亮
Oh! That is amazing.It is so beautiful down there.
由冰晶组成的各种五颜六色的钟乳石
All sorts of colours, beautiful stalactites made of ice crystals
悬挂在冰层的下表面上
hanging down from the top of the ice.
海底形形色色的生物，海星，海胆
All sorts of things on the bottom,starfish, urchins,
不得不让人感叹生命之丰富多样
just an amazing profusion of life.
可爱而且独特，不同于其它的任何地方
Really lovely, totally unique, unlike anywhere else.
不过，一个小时的潜水让我现在感到非常冷
However, after an hour underwater it is getting pretty cold,
帮忙搭把手，行不？ 谢了
so can you give me a hand up, please? Thanks.
未来一个月的时间里，这里还将进行超过100次的潜水
There would be another month here,and over 100 dives,
直到拍摄计划最终完成
before the sequence was eventually completed.